let set7=
[
    {
        question:`1. In the context of plane mirror, consider the following assertions —
        1. An image formed by a plane mirror is erect and of the same size as the object.
        2. In the image formed by a plane mirror, the ‘right’ appears ‘left’ and the ‘left’ appears ‘right’.
        Which of the above assertions is/are correct?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 only',
'B. 2 only',
'C. Both 1 and 2',
'D. Neither 1 nor 2',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: C`,
        exp:`Answer: C
        Explanation: Plane mirrors are simply flat mirrors without curves.
        Because these can be found almost anywhere, the average person is
        incredibly familiar with them (even if they don't know the technical
        term). While the first manmade mirrors were made from intensely
        polished bronze, silver and other metals, today most mirrors are
        made from glass sheets finished with a thin layer of aluminum. That
        said, plane mirrors can be made from liquid as well: Gallium and
        mercury can be used for this purpose. Regardless of material
        construction, however, all flat mirrors function the same way. They
        reflect rays of light, producing an image.
        Characteristics of the image formed by a plane mirror :
         It is virtual
         It is erect and of same size as the object
         The distance of object from the plane mirror is same as the
        distance of image from the plabe mirror.
        One of the important characteristic of the image is that it is
        laterally inverted. It means if you raise your left hand it would
        appear in the plane mirror that you have raised your right hand.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`2. In the context of the different uses of the concave mirror,
        consider the following assertions —
        1. It is used by doctors to examine eyes, ears, nose and throat.
        2. It is used as side mirrors in automobiles.
        Which of the above assertions is/are correct?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 only',
'B. 2 only',
'C. Both 1 and 2',
'D. Neither 1 nor 2',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: A`,
        exp:`Answer: A
        Explanation:
        Concave mirrors are used for many purposes. Doctors use concave
        mirrors for examining eyes, ears, nose and throat. Concave mirrors
        are also used by dentists to see an enlarged image of the teeth. The
        reflectors of torches, headlights of cars and scooters are concave
        in shape.
        Convex mirror is used as side mirrors in automobiles. Convex mirrors
        can form images of objects spread over a large area. So, these help
        the drivers to see the traffic behind them.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`3. In the context of lenses, consider the following assertions —
        1. The image formed by a convex lens is real, inverted and large in
        size than the object.
        2. The image formed by a concave lens is always virtual, erect, and
        smaller in size than the object.
        Which of the above assertions is/are correct?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 only',
'B. 2 only',
'C. Both 1 and 2',
'D. Neither 1 nor 2',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:`Answer: B
        Explanation: The convex lens forms a erect and magnified image.A
        convex lens converges (bends inward) the light generally falling on it.
        Therefore, it is called a converging lens.
        The concave lens always forms a virtual, erect, and smaller in size
        image than the object. The concave lens diverges (bends outward)
        the light and is called a diverging lens.
        Concave Mirror: If a hollow sphere is cut into parts and the outer
        surface of the cut part is painted. Then it becomes a mirror with its
        inner surface as the reflecting surface This kind of mirror is known
        as a concave mirror. Light converges at a point when it strikes and
        reflects back from the reflecting surface of the concave mirror.
        Hence, it is also known as a converging mirror. When the concave
        mirror is placed very close to the object, a magnified and virtual
        image is obtained. But if we increase the distance between the
        object and the mirror then the size of the image reduces and a real
        image is formed. So the image formed by the concave mirror can be
        small or large and it can also be real or virtual.
        Convex Mirror: If the other cut part of the hollow sphere is painted
        from inside, then its outer surface becomes the reflecting surface.
        This kind of mirror is known as convex mirror. A convex mirror is
        also known as a diverging mirror as this mirror diverges light when
        they strike on its reflecting surface. Virtual, erect and diminished
        images are always formed with convex mirrors, irrespective of the
        distance between the object and the mirror. Apart from other
        applications, the convex mirror is mostly used as a rearview mirror in
        vehicles.
        Spherical mirrors are the mirrors having curved surfaces which are
        painted on one of the sides. Spherical mirrors in which inward
        surfaces are painted are known as convex mirrors while the
        spherical mirrors in which outward surfaces are painted are known
        as concave mirrors. Concave mirrors are also known as a converging
        mirror since the rays converge after falling on the concave mirror
        while the convex mirrors are known as diverging mirrors as the rays
        diverge after falling on the convex mirror. In this article, we will
        learn about image formation by concave and convex mirrors.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`4. Consider the following:
        1. Refraction
        2. Reflection
        3. Diffraction
        Which of the above is/are necessary for an image formation in a
        mirror?
        `,
        options:
        [
            'A. 1 and 2 only',
'B. 2 only',
'C. 1 and 3 only',
'D.1, 2 and 3',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:`Answer: B
        Explanation: When a ray of light approaches a smooth polished
        surface and the light ray bounces back, it is called the reflection of
        light. The incident light ray which lands upon the surface is said to
        be reflected off the surface. The ray that bounces back is called
        the reflected ray. If a perpendicular were to be drawn on reflecting
        surface, it would be called normal. The figure below shows the
        reflection of an incident beam on a plane mirror.Image formation on
        a mirror is caused by reflection. Refraction and diffraction have no
        role to play in it.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`5. Humans can see objects when`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Light falls on the object',
'B. Light falls on the human’s eyes',
'C. When light falls on the object and travels to the eye of the human',
'D. None of the above',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: C`,
        exp:`Answer: C
        Explanation: We can see the objects only when light falls on the
        object, and is then reflected to the eyes.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`6. What happens when light energy bends as it passes from one type of substance to another type?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Reflection',
'B. Absorption',
'C. Transmission',
'D. Refraction',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: D`,
        exp:`Answer: D
        Explanation: Refraction is the bending of a wave when it enters a
        medium where its speed is different. We can define it as:Refraction
        is the change in direction of a wave passing from one medium to
        another or from a gradual change in the medium
        Refraction of light is one of the most usually observed
        phenomena which includes refraction of light through prism, but
        other waves like sound waves and water waves also experience
        refraction.
        Laws of Refraction of Light:
        Laws of refraction state that:
        1. The incident ray, refracted ray, and the normal to the interface
        of two media at the point of incidence all lie on the same plane.
        2. The ratio of sine of angle of incidence to the sine of angle of
        refraction is a constant. This is also known as Snell’s law of
        refraction.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`7. What might explain why light travels in a straight line?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Light waves travel in a straight line because sound waves travel in a straight line.',
'B. If there is nothing to interfere with light waves, they will travel in a straight line.',
'C. Light waves don’t travel in a straight line.',
'D. Light waves will always travel in a straight line, even if they come into contact with another object.',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: D`,
        exp:`Answer: D
        Explanation: Once light has been produced, it will keep travelling in
        a straight line until it hits something else. Shadows are evidence of
        light travelling in straight lines. An object blocks light so that it
        can’t reach the surface where we see the shadow. Light fills up all of
        the space before it hits the object, but the whole region between
        the object and the surface is in shadow. Shadows don’t appear
        totally dark because there is still some light reaching the surface
        that has been reflected off other objects.
        Once light has hit another surface or particles, it is then absorbed,
        reflected (bounces off), scattered (bounces off in all directions),
        refracted (direction and speed changes) or transmitted (passes
        straight through).
        `
    },
    {
        question:`8. What is the power of concave lens?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Positive',
'B. Negative',
'C. Both',
'D. None of the above',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:`Answer: B
        Explanation: A concave lens is a lens that possesses at least one
        surface that curves inwards. It is a diverging lens, meaning that it
        spreads out light rays that have been refracted through it. A
        concave lens is thinner at its centre than at its edges, and is used to
        correct short-sightedness (myopia).
        After light rays have passed through the lens, they appear to come
        from a point called the principal focus. This is the point onto which
        the collimated light that moves parallel to the axis of the lens is
        focused. The image formed by a concave lens is virtual, meaning that
        it will appear to be farther away than it actually is, and therefore
        smaller than the object itself. Curved mirrors often have this
        effect, which is why many (especially on cars) come with a warning:
        Objects in mirror are closer than they appear. The image will also be
        upright, meaning not inverted, as some curved reflective surfaces
        and lenses have been known to do.The lens formula that is used to
        work out the position and nature of an image formed by a lens can be
        expressed as follows: 1/u + 1/v = 1/f, where u and v are the
        distances of the object and image from the lens, respectively, and f
        is the focal length of the lens.
        `
    },
    {
        question:`9. What type of a mirror is used in anti-shop-lifting-devices?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Concave mirror',
'B. Convex mirror',
'C. Plane mirror',
'D. None of the above',

        ],
        answer:`Answer: B`,
        exp:`Answer: B`
    },
    {
        question:`10. Due to which phenomena the stick if immersed in water appears to be bent?`,
        options:
        [
            'A. Reflection',
'B. Dispersion',
'C. Refraction',
'D. Scattering',
        ],
        answer:`Answer: C`,
        exp:`Answer: C`
    }
]